good morning welcome to meditating with
John brevity I'm a cognitive
psychologist and a cognitive scientist
at the University of Toronto there I
teach and scientifically study phenomena
like mindfulness and related phenomena
like Insight flow mystical experience
transformative experience higher states
of consciousness cultivation of wisdom
and the aspiration toward enlightenment
I've been practicing the past Nam
meditation that a contemplation touch
each one and she come for over 29 years
and teaching them professionally for
close to 20 years welcome this is a
progressive course what that means is on
Mondays our Dharma days I've taught
practices and principles that build on
previous practical practices and
principles so if you're joining us for
the first time of course you're welcome
to stay but I suggest going on to the
links in description
going back to lesson 1 and working
through the lessons and that way you can
catch up with the rest of us as of next
week we're shifting our schedule next
Monday is completely off because it's a
holiday so we won't be sitting that they
enjoyed enjoy the time for yourself guys
and then thereafter every so the
following Monday will be a dharma day
and then every other Monday every
alternative Monday will be at Dharma day
and will continue going for quite some
time so a couple of things please
remember to like this video stream ought
to increase its visibility on the
YouTube algorithm today at the end of
every sit there are Q&A some days are
longer than others
Monday and Wednesdays and Fridays can it
be longer especially Mondays and
Wednesdays Tuesdays and Thursdays a
little bit shorter for the Q&A is at the
end of this session please keep it
limited to you know that the set of
practices and principles I've been
teaching you in this course for more
encompassing questions are welcome that
you join me today at 3 p.m. Eastern Time
live stream on YouTube where I will
answer more comprehensive questions
about all of my work comprehensively so
I welcome you to you to that later today
I'm trying to think of anything else
our house put anything else that I need
to say I think that's good I think we're
ready to go so please set your phones to
do not disturb and get your posture
ready and we'll begin when I say it
again begin
slowly commodity practice trying as best
you can to integrate what you cultivated
in your practice with the everyday
consciousness and cognition
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
okay good let's take some questions
please I'm miss F I can't as several
continents in a row after a vowel so I
can't really pronounce it is the flow
from method to the past and priors not
related to the flow between the breath
Davonte and the breath of the whole
abdomen and the flow element of the core
floor yes is so that's that that flow
you're getting sort of within your body
while you're doing the the pasta you
know finding your flow in preparation
for basically pasta or for any
mindfulness practice is the same kind of
flow you're feeling within the in the
movement within and without that's
exactly right
that's exactly right it should be the
same type of flow that's what I mean
when I talk about how the dynamic ground
of the body is taken up into these
practices the body isn't left behind
strainer I'm planning a retreat with
friends silent 10-day a sitting day not
my first deal recommendations but which
practice is to use to alternate will
there be tips in the guidebook so um
it's a good thing it's a good idea to
have somebody who's leading a retreat
who's had on some personal extensive
practice with it and then it's good idea
to have somebody there that has some
psychotherapeutic training because
sometimes in retreat things not for
people and stuff comes out so retreats
are very powerful that's why people do
them but like anything powerful it could
have unexpected consequences so it's
it's a good thing you know you can see
some pretty dramatic behavior at times
so it's good to have that there and also
be able to answer people's questions
because they'll often confront some very
challenging states I would recommend if
you're going to do it if people are
unfamiliar I would recommend just
teaching them the the core four of the
base and the base
possibly know if they've done other you
know they're quite advanced then you
might try the alternation but pasta
practice going into deeper pasta a
matter practice and then oppression of
practice and then I would recommend if
you can getting somebody who could lead
people through a moving mindful it's got
just tai chi yoga Leeson Chi cung be a
good idea here are Kroger fellow Kyra if
something comes up that I need to
address with my therapist iPhone become
fertile for my eyes and continue to the
five part is impart mindfulness is that
okay yes so when you are doing this
practice in conjunction with therapy it
is good to have what Kyra said there's
good to have some bridging practices
between the city and the therapist tell
the therapist as I said make sure the
therapist knows you're doing this and
right in get them on board but what Kyra
said is is having a kind of bridging
practice between them that's very good
try to note so good yes I'll try to note
though if it starts to accelerate and
when it's happening because that if that
is that you're there's a chance that
you're being sort of your monkey Minds
found a way sort of sneaking in and and
sort of like slave hand side of hand and
tricking you
okay um that's only even if you notice
the frequency of this starts to increase
but other than that that's a very good
kind of bridging practice for sure
ah Julian Weinstein when we go from for
passing to Metta with one single breath
that feels like a lot of effort team
versus simple sensation mindfulness are
noting like adding concepts to the
meditation how do we allow that process
to happen without forcing it so that's
why I said it's very very important to
significantly lower your standards
initially in the sense that you're just
except you're going to get a very
shallow Metta a very shallow but pasta I
think that the effort there is probably
because you're trying to get you know
the deep Metta and the deeper person you
have when you're just doing the partner
Metta
that's that's too much that's too much
and as for concept don't think of
concepts things I think about movement
of mind sir
opening the mind out and then it right
opening awareness out opening attention
out opening your sense of what's present
out not anything particular just that
opening and then melting to the core
opening and then melting to the core so
don't try and do concepts try to try to
rye the motion of the mind that's in
sync with the motion of the breath but
try to accept that you're not going to
get the deeper past not and a deep meta
until you've been practicing this for a
very long time hopefully that will help
another question from strana the deeper
person becomes really hard for me I lose
the breath in my Dottie and as an anchor
I feel like I become cut off from body
awareness sensation much of I like this
is this normal
yes it is normal it's normal for us when
we lose so you have the orientation
association area in the brain
according to Newberg and others this
tells you where you are and very often
when we get it to deeper person though
we lose that now you don't lose the body
because the body is actually you know
it's energetically present I don't like
using word energy I mean metabolic and
cognitive information processing energy
I don't mean anything strange or weird
but it's so the body is present that way
if you try to pick up on the energetic
aspects so that can often help but it is
very challenge for people with their
sense of you know their body and who and
where they are and I mentioned this
they're sort of you know you're in your
embodying your embody ego and there's
nothing wrong with I'm not criticizing
insulting but your body evil can drop
away mind and body drop away as doujin
famously said and that it can be a very
very disconcerting experience so you
know maybe don't do deep the pasta too
much maybe just a little bit as always
you know very probative slowly trying to
shift slowly slowly slowly and right you
know that you're losing the sense of a
body
more that scent like I said right
there's still the the power of
presencing itself sort of becomes your
body Herren Agustin said I feel myself
automatically meditating when falling
asleep unis tips oh well that's that's
interesting
yeah that's it's a really challenging
one automatically and then the I guess I
mean it's a very it's it's really
strongly recommended that you don't
meditate before you fall asleep because
as I said you'll associate meditation
was falling asleep are you noticing
their reverse at all that your brain is
maybe moving towards sleepiness when
you're meditating because that's that's
a definite warning sign so I would
suggest that you maybe prep you maybe
give your your you mind another thing to
do rather than meditated so one thing
that's very good because it gets you
more into the frame for REM is to read
some fiction read some narrative before
going to sleep and we head to the point
where you're really tired then see you
can just drop away from the narrative
into sleep rather than going into
meditation hopefully that won't train
you to associate sleepiness with reading
Gabriel reasons done and prior to that
it I find it feels like there's some
physical movement in my mind possibly my
eyes they're focusing near or farther is
this okay I can avoid it but it seems to
help god my thought yeah that's okay
those kinesthetic images those are like
I said they're you know remember I
mentioned this when we have images that
are like lenses we're not looking at
them but we're looking through it by
means of them and eventually you won't
need that probably but right now if it's
helping that's fine that's fine that's
your brain basically enacting you know
all of the mind and the body are like
this right and whenever you doing
something mental you're making use of a
potential wave in which you can if you
can embody actually this is called the
inactive view of mine it's very it's one
of a core idea in cognitive science
right now so that that's fine that's fun
nabela is there an order to the five
factors have been pouring mindfulness
like you said that the vigilance is the
core yes there is definitely do
vigilance and then sensitivity first get
everything flowing then acuity then
noticing the three aspects the three
fields of reaction and and reminding is
the fifth but only in the sense you're
always trying to keep in mind fulness
not go into inference theorizing
justification explaining commenting
exaggerated so thank you everyone for
joining it's always a great pleasure to
do this I always want to thank my dear
friend and techno major mark my beloved
son Jason please subscribe to the
channel to be notified of the next
videos also on the channel you'll find
awakening from the meaning crisis which
is a lecture series and voices with
verve a key which is a discussion series
that you know address many of these
topics on a greater depth and connect
them to other topics that I think are
ultimately relevant for the cultivation
of wisdom pleasing by others who might
benefit by sharing this series please
also like this video stream that will
help there is a discord server to chat
with others there's a discord server
that has been set up by Brett and
pleasure of the doubt pleasure of doubt
and he is doing an excellent job at it
and it's basically dedicated to people
who are sort of following my work
awakening for the meeting crisis with
Reiki also following this meditation of
course so there's a good place to meet
people people of good faith who want to
discuss this in good discussion to a
good depth reminder we're not doing this
Monday it's a holiday Victoria Day here
in which I guess we're celebrating the
British Empire it's kind of absurd I
guess but anyways other than that though
we do this every 9:30 a.m. Eastern Time
funding please remember
continuity of practice more important
than quantity of practice there is no
enemy worse
on there's no friend no Ally greater
than your own mind take care everyone
I'll see you on Tuesday